School of Kinesiology fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
School of Kinesiology fonds
1966 - 1979
F-60
50 cm of textual records 2 photographs: black and white negatives; 9.5 x 12 cm 6 architectural drawings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Department of Biomedical Physiology and Kinesiology
When Simon Fraser University opened in 1965, it established a Physical Development Centre in the Faculty of Education. This Centre included Physical Development Studies, which was first chaired by Dr. Glen Kirchner. This unit was physically located on the top of the gymnasium complex with laboratories in the gymnasium and across campus.
In September 1967, SFU instituted the degree of Bachelor of Science (Kinesiology) intended for students interested in becoming physical education specialists, or pursuing graduate studies and research. It was the first interdisciplinary program in this field to be offered in North America.
The Department of Physical Studies was split in 1970, when those faculty with an interest in physical education transferred to the Professional Development Centre within the Faculty of Education. The remaining faculty became the Department of Kinesiology with Dr. Eric Banister as its first chair. This was the first Department of Kinesiology in Canada. The specialist in dance moved to the Centre for the Arts, later re-named the School for the Contemporary Arts. The Department remained in the Faculty of Education administratively although the B.Sc. program was under the direction of the Interdisciplinary Committee on Kinesiology chaired by the Dean of Science. The mandate then was changed to the study of humans structure and function.
In 1972 the Department of Kinesiology was moved to the newly-established Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies. After Dr. Banister's term as Chair had ended, he was replaced by Dr. Tom Calvert, who remained as chair until he became Dean of the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies in 1977. At this point, Dr. Eric Banister returned for a further term as Chair of the department.
In 1976 the physical location of the department was moved to the top floor of the Library Building with laboratories in various locations across campus. It wasn't until 1981 that the department moved to its current building, the Shrum Science Centre, with offices and laboratories in the same location. There has been modest expanison of laborartory and office space since that time. In 1982 Dr. John Dickinson became Chairman of the Department, and in 1985 the academic location of Kinesiology was changed when the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies was disbanded. Kinesiology became a School in the new Faculty of Applied Sciences. Dr. Andy Hoffer was appointed as the new Director of the School in 1991. Dr. John Dickinson returned as Director in 1997. Dr Jim Morrison took over as Director from 2000 to 2002 after which Dr. John Dickinson was re-appointed for a three-year term.
During the 33 years of its history, the School of Kinesiology has seen steady growth in terms of student numbers and in terms of faculty size. The first Masters student was graduated in 1970 and the first Ph.D. student in l980. As of 1998, approximately 500 undergraduate students and 50 graduate students study Kinesiology at SFU.
published
Full
Revised
Title based on the content of the fonds.
Fonds consists of records arising from the activities of the Department of Kinesiology. Fonds includes correspondence, memos, reports, proposals, financial records and architectural plans relating to provisions for the study of Kinesiology at SFU. The fonds also includes records created by the Interdisciplinary Committee on Kinesiology as well as correspondence relating to the professional interests of E.W. Banister while Chair of the Department.
The series were created by the Archivist to reflect the structure and functions of the creating body.
Calvert, Thomas W.; Banister, Eric W.; Architectural drawings; Photographic materials; Textual records
Additional material has been accessioned but not yet processed (as of September 2002: 1.67 m., 1970-1987). Please consult the archivist for information about using these materials; restrictions may apply. Further accruals are expected.
Consult the fonds of the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, F-23.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and unit lists are available.
- Interdisciplinary Committee in Kinesiology, 1966 - 1970; F-60-1; 4 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records arising from the activities of the Interdisciplinary Committee on Kinesiology. Series includes minutes of meetings, correspondence, reports and proposals relating to the development of staff and resources to facilitate the study of Kinesiology at the University.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - Proposed interdisciplinary program: study of human movement, 1966 - 1967; F-60-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Interdisciplinary committee on Kinesiology 1/3, 1966 - 1970; F-60-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Interdisciplinary committee on Kinesiology 2/3, 1966 - 1970; F-60-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Interdisciplinary committee on Kinesiology 3/3, 1966 - 1970; F-60-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
- Chair's correspondence, 1970 - 1977; F-60-2; 39 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records arising from the administrative activities of the Chair of the Department of Kinesiology. Series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence as well as memos, minutes of departmental meetings, and financial statements. In addition, the series includes correspondence relating to professional research interests of Chair E.W. Banister.
  - Chair's correspondence, 1970 - 1971; F-60-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1971; F-60-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1971 - 1972; F-60-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1972; F-60-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1972; F-60-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 60-1)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973; F-60-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1973 - 1974; F-60-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence - Departmental meetings, 1973 - 1976; F-60-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1974; F-60-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 60-2)
  - Chair's correspondence 1/3, 1974 - 1975; F-60-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence 2/3, 1974 - 1975; F-60-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence 3/3, 1974 - 1975; F-60-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence - Athletic testing program, 1975; F-60-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence - B.C. Medical fitness proposal, 1975 - 1976; F-60-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence - Continuing Studies, 1975; F-60-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence - Continuing Studies, 1975 - 1976; F-60-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Chair's correspondence, 1976 - 1977; F-60-2-0-0-27
- Subject files, 1969 - 1979; F-60-3; 15 cm of textual records
  Series consists of subject files created by the Department of Kinesiology relating to departmental activities such as course and program development, research, and assisting students in matters such as employment. Series includes reports and essays as well as program and course proposals and evaluations.
  - Woodward Project re Presymptomatic Diagnostic Centre, 1969; F-60-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - External Review, 1973; F-60-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Man-Machine Study at Bel-Par Industries, 1974; F-60-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Proposal for a Ph.D. in Kinesiology, 1974; F-60-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Proposal for a Ph.D. in Kinesiology, 1974; F-60-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 60-3)
  - Recommendations for the 'Safe' Usage of Electricity in the Life Sciences -, 1974; F-60-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Biochemistry Curriculum Committee, 1975 - 1976; F-60-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Course Evaluations, 1975 - 1977; F-60-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Course Offerings, 1975 - 1977; F-60-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Graduate Program, 1975; F-60-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Proposed Minor and Certificate Programs, 1975 - 1977; F-60-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Critique of Proposed Univeristy of Victoria Program, 1977; F-60-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Youth Employment Program, 1977; F-60-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Research and Ethics, 1978; F-60-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Universities Council of B.C. Visit to Department of Kinesiology, 1979; F-60-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Opportunities for Kinesiology Graduates, F-60-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Remedial Gymnastics Degree, F-60-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Rehabilitation Science Graduate Program, F-60-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Kinesiology Undergraduate Student Manual, F-60-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
- Facilities, 1972 - 1976; F-60-4; 3 cm of textual records 2 photographs: black and white negatives, 9.5 x 12 cm. 6 architectural drawings; Physical description: 2 photographs (negatives) located in F-60-4-0-1
  Series consists of records relating to the physical facilities of the Department of Kinesiology. Series includes correspondence, memos, financial records, photographs and architectural plans.
  - Phase IV Construction 1/2, 1972 - 1976; F-60-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Phase IV Construction 2/2, 1972 - 1976; F-60-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Environmental Physiology Unit, 1976; F-60-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 60-4)
  - Facilities and equipment, 1975 - 1976; F-60-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 60-4)